Guide to the Jill "Billy" Rainsford Papers 1922-1991 MSS.030
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jill "Billy" Rainsford Papers
1922-1991
Fales Library and Special Collections
Rainsford, Jill (Marguerite), 1905-1994
MSS.030
4 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 3 flat boxes.
Jill Rainsford (1905-1994) was born Marguerite Rainsford (known as Billy), in Brooklyn. She was an actress, songwriter, painter and author, and was prominent in New York's Vaudeville theater and motion picture industry during the 1920s both as an actress and songwriter. The collection includes an unpublished autobiography, correspondence, sheet music and a large number of photographs and memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Jill "Billy" Rainsford Papers were donated to New York University in 1995 by her sister Doris Rainsford of Athens, Ohio. The accession number associated with this gift is 1994.030
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into seven series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1922-1991
Series II: Music
Series III: Memorabilia
Series IV: Photographic Material
Series V: Julia S. Rainsford Papers
Series VI: 'I Was There Charlie' Manuscript
Series VII: Oversize Material
Biographical Note
Jill Rainsford (1905-1994) born Marguerite Rainsford and known as Billy, was an actress, songwriter, painter and author. Born in Brooklyn, she was the second child of Henry and Julia Rainsford and from an early age aspired to a career on the stage beginning violin and dance lessons at age 8. Her sister Doris, 4 years her senior was devoted to Billy and was her nearly constant companion throughout her life.
Billy was a member of New York's famous Kiddie Klub and performed with such stars as Paulette Goddard, Gene Raymond, and Arlin Riggin, the former Olympic champion. She honed her dance techniques in Rutherford High School Productions, and by 1922, at the age of 17, she had joined Pat Rooney's "Rings of Smoke" Vaudeville act portraying the "French girl" on a cross-country tour.
The tour gave her valuable Vaudeville experience which led her to the nascent film industry and the D.W. Griffith Company in Mamaroneck, New York. She landed the role of the dancing Indian Princess in Griffith's classic film "America," and appeared in "Sally of the Sawdust." In addition she worked with Griffith plotting scenes for his leading actress Carol Dempster.
When the Griffith Studio closed, Billy continued her silent film career at other New York studios including: the Spitz, Pathe, Famous Players-Lasky, and Tech Art starring with Dexter McReynolds, Charley Bowers, Fatty Lehman, and Duncan Renaldo. She also did some modeling during this period, most notably for the artist Bradshaw Crandell, who painted several magazine and calendar covers of Billy, as well as, the pastel portrait in the collection.
When the film industry moved to the west coast, Billy remained in New York with her mother and her sister and began appearing in nightclub acts in many of New York's famous nightclubs including Don Dickerman's Pirate's Den and Country Fair Clubs in Greenwich Village.
Following a brief marriage and the birth of her son Richard Rainsford, she performed on the cruise ship circuit to Havana. Wanting to spend more time with her only child, Billy began a profitable business of writing song lyrics for notable song writers such as Arthur Gutman, Gilbert Wall, Ray Dallas, and performers such as Spivy LeVoe, Florence Herbert, Harriet Hutchins, Beth Challis, and Irene Bordoni.
Later in life Billy went on to own a wholesale antiques shop in upstate New York which she ran with her son and her sister. Billy and Doris then followed Richard's academic career and eventually ended up in Ohio where Billy painted miniature landscapes and wrote her unpublished autobiography 'I Was There Charlie'.
Jill "Billy" Rainsford died on July 5, 1994 at the age of 89.
Scope and Contents
The small but rich collection of materials which comprises the Jill "Billy" Rainsford Papers, 1905-1994, in New York University's Fales Library reflects the many aspects of her life: actress, songwriter, painter and author.
The papers offer a glance into New York's Vaudeville theatre and motion picture industry during the 1920s. Lyrics and music scores document Rainsford's career as a songwriter in the 1930s. A large portion of the collection consists of photographs and memorabilia which adds a visual dimension to the collection. Rainsford's unpublished autobiography provides her own, often witty, insights on her life.
The papers of Julia D. Rainsford, mother of Jill "Billy" Rainsford provide information on turn of the century New York and include a variety of playbills from New York theaters and opera houses. A trip diary provides information on cross-country travel in the early 1900s.
The seven series which comprise the Papers of Jill "Billy" Rainsford are measured in linear feet. Each series has a descriptive note and a container list. Following the container lists for the series is a list of oversize materials separated from the rest of the collection. Oversize materials are cross-referenced from their originating series.
Separated Materials
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Film stills.; New York (N.Y.).; Sheet music.; Theater programs.; Souvenir programs.; Entertainers -- United States -- Biography; Popular music -- 1921-1930; Dance music -- United States; Instrumental Music.; Motion pictures.; Silent films; Vaudeville -- United States -- 20th century; Vaudeville -- United States -- History -- Sources; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Songs with piano.; Theater -- New York (State); Revues -- United States; Bordoni, Irene; Chambers, Ralph; Crandell, Bradshaw; Bowers, Charles R., 1889-1946; Capra, Frank, 1897-1991; Dickerman, Donald Horace, 1893-; Gish, Lillian, 1893-1993; D.W. Griffith, Inc.; Diamondo, Jim; Rainsford family; Rainsford, Doris; Goddard, Paulette, 1911-1990; Griffith, D. W. (David Wark), 1875-1948; Rainsford, Richard.; Rainsford, Julia.; Rainsford, Jill (Marguerite), 1905-1994; Spivy, Madame, 1907-1971; Rooney, Pat, 1880-1962
- Series One: Correspondence, 1922-1991
  Scope and Contents
  Subseries A corresponds to the time when Billy was active in show business. It is arranged chronologically. Within this subseries one folder is arranged by subject: the "Rings of Smoke" tour and includes letters written to J.D. Rainsford from Billy.
  Subseries B is divided into subject files and includes: general correspondence, art and writing correspondence, "personal and meaningful" correspondence, and letters to publishers. Each file is arranged chronologically. Of special note are the letters Billy wrote and received from Lillian Gish and Frank Capra (1 each) as she was preparing to write her manuscript. These letters are located in the "personal and meaningful correspondence" file.
  Subseries C is arranged by correspondent and chronologically within each folder for any one person who wrote a substantial number of letters to Billy.
  - Subseries A. General Correspondence, 1922-1938
    - Billy to J.D. Rainsford, from Rooney Tour (removed from series 5)1922 - 1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence to Billy from family, friends, and admirers, 1922 - 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence to Billy from family, friends, and admirers, 1925 - 1938, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B. General Correspondence, 1968-1991
    - Art and Writing Correspondence, 1968 - 1991, bulk 1987 - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1980 - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Personal and Meaningful Correspondence, 1949 - 1991, bulk circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Publishers 1988 - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Drafts of Letters to Publishers 1988 - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries C. General Correspondence, by correspondent
    - Irene Bordoni to Billy 1936 - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - R.W. Chambers to Billy, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jim Diamondo to Billy, 1971 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Don Dickerman to Billy, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Richard Rainsford to Billy, greeting cards, n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series Two: Music, circa 1930
  Subseries A includes lyrics, mostly typewritten, and in many cases revisions. These are arranged alphabetically by song title and include such titles as; "Contented Cows", "I Want to be Bad", and "The Subway Masher".
  Subseries B includes handwritten music scores. Many accompany the lyrics found in subseries A. Music scores are arranged alphabetically by title, with the exception of one folder which contains music written by Billy and Jim Diamondo. Also included in subseries B is multiple copies of the sheet music for "High Flight" (music written by Jim Diamondo).
  Subseries C includes business records relating to song lyrics, including handwritten lists and records of sales and some correspondence to the Library of Congress for copyrights.
  - Subseries A. Music Lyrics
    - Song Lyrics, Arranged by title, A - H, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Song Lyrics, Arranged by title, I - Z, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries B. Music Scores
    - Music Scores, Arranged by title, A - H, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Music Scores, Arranged by title, I - P, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Music Scores, Arranged by title, Q - Z, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Music Scores, Billy and Jim Diamondo, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sheet Music (with duplicate copies) to "High Flight", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries C. Music Records
    - Music business records, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series Three: Memorabilia
  Series Three is arranged by form and subject. It includes programs highlighting Billy's tour with Pat Rooney, D.W. Griffith programs, and Kiddie Klub programs and a scrapbook documenting Billy's career kept by Doris. Various magazines in which Billy appeared and a folder of newspaper clippings documenting her stage career and personal events in her life are also included. Several oversized magazines were moved to series seven. Boxed jewelry (series three, item 18, scarabs) are housed in Box 4, series six.
  - Programs from Kiddie Klub and Brooklyn Lodge performances (duplicates removed from scrapbook), 1918 - 1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Programs from Rutherford High School and local productions, 1916 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Programs from "Rings of Smoke" tour, 1922 - 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Programs from D.W. Griffith productions including America and "The Fall of Babylon"., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Loose pages of a scrapbook, Harry Stower woodcut, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Actors Directory and Studio Guide, November 1925 and March 1926, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - True Story Magazine 1925, (photographs of Rainsford on pages 40 - 42, photographs of Uma Merkel p 19 - 21). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Judge Magazine, December 4, 1926 (caricature of Rainsford on page 17) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pirates Den, 1927?, Cruise Ship Programs 1933, Strip Tease Program (Billy wrote song for production)., 1927-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook of Billy's early career, Kiddie Klub and Pat Rooney period., undated (Box 1, Folder 11 - 17)
  - Scarabs--gift from Kitty Donner, 1938 (moved to box 4) (Box 1, Folder (Item) 18)
  - Jill "Billy" Rainsford framed pastel drawing, undated; MSS.030.cuid21365 (Box 6, Object MSS.030.cuid21365)
- Series Four: Photographic Material
  Series Four includes mainly 8" x 10" photographs that are arranged in folders by type of photo (ie, portraits/publicity or movie stills). Movie stills are arranged by film title whenever possible. Larger photographs, which include portraits by Russell Ball are arranged chronologically.
  - Photo album: Rainsford family, Billy as child, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Billy's notes and lists of photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - America, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sally of the Sawdust, "That Royle Girl", and publicity photo for "Orphans of the Storm"., undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Barbara Lamar film (1924) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Song of the Southern States (1925) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - M.W. Balfe (1925) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Radio Mad (1925) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Caught in the Act, undated (Box 2, Folder 9 - 10)
  - The Mask, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Yellow Rose, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Charley Bowers' film (1926) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous movie stills, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Portraits and publicity stills, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Portraits and publicity stills - - duplicates, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Don Dickerman Country Fair and Pirate's Den and 1930s nightclub act, ca.1930 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Trip to Havana (1927) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Stills of Other People, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Negatives and pieces of film, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Contact sheets of photos in collection, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Loose oversized items
    - Rings of Smoke, undated (Box 3, Folder 1 - 3)
    - Publicity portraits for "Rings of Smoke", undated (Box 3, Folder 4 - 7)
    - America, undated (Box 3, Folder 8 - 9)
    - The Captive Prince, undated (Box 3, Folder 10 - 11)
    - Portraits of Billy signed by Russell Ball, undated (Box 3, Folder 12 - 16)
    - The Mask, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Yellow Rose, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Portraits, undated (Box 3, Folder 19 - 20)
    - Rainsford/Dickerman Country Fair Act, undated (Box 3, Folder 21 - 26)
    - Duplicates, undated (Box 3, Folder 27 - 29)
- Series Five: Julia D. Rainsford Papers
  Series Five includes correspondence arranged by "subject" and time period and arranged chronologically within each file. German language letters are grouped together. One folder comprises the Rainsford family papers which includes the marriage license of Henry and Julia Rainsford, citizenship papers of the maternal grandmother of Rainsford, and family burial plot information. A diary of a family cross country trip during 1908-1909 is also included.
  - Correspondence in German, 1853-1883 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Henry Rainsford to Julia,1888 - 1890 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Henry Rainsford to Julia,1891, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Henry Rainsford to Julia,1892 - 1921, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Family Correspondence, 1895 - 1901 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Family Correspondence, 1904 - 1922, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1887 - 1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Bob? to Julia, 1924 - 1926 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Christmas and greeting cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Calling cards, ephemera, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Julia and Doris Rainsford's poems and jingles, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rainsford Family Papers, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Songbook, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Trip diary, 1908 - 1909 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series Six: 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript
  Series Six includes two copies of the 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript. One copy is arranged in folders for easy access, the other copy remains boxed. Research notes precede the manuscript and contain a synopsis of the manuscript.
  - Research notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 1 - 2)
  - 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript, Chapters 1 and 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript, Chapters 3 and 4, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript, Chapters 5 and 6, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript, Chapters 7 and 8, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript, Chapters 9 and 10, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - I was there Charlie manuscript, Chapters 11 and 12, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - I was there Charlie manuscript, Chapters 13 and 14, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - I was there Charlie manuscript, Chapters 15 and 16, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 'I Was There Charlie' manuscript, Chapter 17, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - (2) 5 1/4 inch floppy discs of manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Boxed copy of manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Series Seven: Oversized Material
  Series Six is arranged by subject and form, and includes Bradshaw Crandall magazine and calendar covers, copies of magazines which feature Billy (1922-1923), and theatre and opera programs collected by Julia Rainsford. A briefcase which belonged to Billy is also included.
  - Bradshaw Crandall calendar and magazine covers; handwritten music score to "High Flight", music store bag which held copies of sheet music., undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Magazines: New York Clipper, June 28, 1922; New York Star, March 31, 1923 (3 copies); Billboard, April 21, 1923, 1922-1923 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Theatre and Opera Programs collected by J.D. Rainsford, 1873 - 1898, bulk 1886 - 1888 (Box 5, Folder 3 - 4)
  - Briefcase - - gift from Doris to Billy for lyrics., undated (Box 5, Folder (Item) 5)